Civil Rights History Project collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 2: Interviews
  - John Carlos oral history interview conducted by David P. Cline in New York, New York, August 18, 2013
    Biographical History: John Carlos was a member of the American Olympic track team and was the Bronze Medalist at the 1968 Summer Olympics in Mexico, where he protested racism around the world. He later played football in the NFL, and worked as a counselor and track and field coach.
    Summary: John Carlos discusses his childhood in Harlem, New York, the changes that he saw in Harlem with the widespread use of heroin and the splintering of families, and describes the disparities in education for black children when he was growing up. He remembers the influence of black leaders including Marcus Garvey, Malcolm X, and Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. Carlos was recruited to run track at East Texas State University, where he experienced racial discrimination and was treated poorly by his coach. He explains his protest at the 1968 Olympics, including the symbols that he and Tommy Smith employed to protest racial discrimination, and he describes the emotional impact that the protest had on him.
    - Moving Images, 9 video files of 9 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (127 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0103_mv01-09
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (68 pages); afc2010039_crhp0103_Carlos_transcript
  - Ekwueme Michael Thelwell oral history interview conducted by Emilye Crosby in Pelham, Massachusetts, August 23, 2013
    Biographical History: Dr. Ekwueme Michael Thelwell is a scholar, activist, writer, and administrator at the University of Massachusetts Amherst. He served as a staff member of the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) and worked as a civil rights activist in the deep South and in Washington, D.C.
    Summary: Ekwueme Michael Thelwell remembers his time as a student activist at Howard University and his experiences with the Nonviolent Action Group (NAG), the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC), and the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party (MFDP). Working primarily out of Washington, D.C., Thelwell marched in and organized demonstrations and made major contributions to SNCC and MFDP strategy around voter registration and the MFDP's 1965 effort to challenge the seating of the Mississippi congressional delegation. He details the developing MFDP strategy, his attempts to navigate Washington politics, and his relationships with various figures involved in the effort.
    - Moving Images, 24 video files of 24 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (255 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0104_mv01-24
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (116 pages); afc2010039_crhp0104_Thelwell_transcript
  - Virginia Simms George oral history interview conducted by Emilye Crosby in Northborough, Massachusetts, August 24, 2013
    Biographical History: Virginia Simms George was a civil rights activist in Richmond, Virginia, and later a human resource professional, teacher, counselor in Massachusetts.
    Summary: Virginia Simms George remembers growing up in segregated Newport News, Virginia, attending Virginia Union University, and her desire to become a lawyer. She recalls participating in a protest at Thalhimers department store in Richmond, Virginia. She discusses her work as a teacher, counselor, and volunteering for many organizations. She also discusses the commemoration of the protests in Richmond, and her thoughts on racism and other civil rights issues today.
    - Moving Images, 6 video files of 6 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (73 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0105_mv01-06
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (43 pages); afc2010039_crhp0105_George_transcript
  - Robert J. Brown oral history interview conducted by David P. Cline in High Point, North Carolina, October 1, 2013
    Biographical History: Robert J. Brown was a police officer and founder of B & C Associates, Inc., a public relations firm.
    Summary: Robert Brown describes his childhood in High Point, North Carolina, the poverty and segregation that defined his childhood, and how his grandmother influenced him by telling stories about his family's history during slavery. Brown became one of the first black policemen in High Point and later transitioned to a position as a federal agent in New York. He returned to North Carolina in 1960 to start a public relations firm, B & C Associates, Inc., which advised companies about how to change policies on race and segregation. Brown also shares stories about serving as a special assistant to President Richard Nixon and his role in bringing attention to apartheid in South Africa through his relationship with Nelson Mandela and his family.
    - Moving Images, 11 video files of 11 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (130 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0106_mv01-11
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (59 pages); afc2010039_crhp0106_Brown_transcript
  - Harry Blake oral history interview conducted by David P. Cline in Shreveport, Louisiana, October 3, 2013
    Biographical History: The Reverend Harry Blake is the pastor of Mt. Canaan Baptist Church in Shreveport, Louisiana. He served as the first field secretary of the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC) and as president of the Louisiana Baptist State Convention and General Secretary of the National Baptist Convention, USA, Inc.
    Summary: The Reverend Doctor Harry Blake discusses his childhood on a plantation in Louisiana in the 1930s and 1940s and how he became a leader in the Civil Rights Movement in Shreveport, Louisiana. Blake joined the Southern Christian Leadership Conference in 1960 after he heard Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr., give a speech at Bishop College in Texas, where he was a student. Blake discusses his pastorate at Mount Canaan Baptist Church in Shreveport, how he came to develop a good relationship with local politicians, and the work he continues to do within the context of the civil rights struggle.
    - Moving Images, 4 video files of 4 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (70 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0107_mv01-04
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (28 pages); afc2010039_crhp0107_Blake_transcript
  - Abernathy family oral history interview conducted by Hasan Kwame Jeffries in Atlanta, Georgia, and Stuttgart, Germany, October 10, 2013
    Biographical History: Donzaleigh Abernathy is an actress, producer, director, and writer in Los Angeles, California.
    Biographical History: Juandalynn R. Abernathy is an opera, concert, and African-American spirituals singer.
    Biographical History: Ralph David Abernathy, III, is a social justice activist, and a former Georgia State Senator and member of the State House of Representatives.
    Summary: Donzaleigh Abernathy, Juandalynn Abernathy, and Ralph Abernathy, III, recall their father, Ralph David Abernathy and their own experiences as children in the Civil Rights Movement. The Abernathy children spent much of their childhoods with the children of Martin Luther King, Jr. Unlike the King children, the Abernathy siblings actively participated in direct action, including the Poor People's Campaign. All three children felt palpably the fear of violence in their everyday lives. This interview offers an intimate portrait of the home of a civil rights icon and of the intense friendship between Abernathy and King.
    - Moving Images, 10 video files of 10 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (118 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0108_mv01-10
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (65 pages); afc2010039_crhp0108_Abernathy_transcript
  - Wyatt Tee Walker oral history interview conducted by David P. Cline in Richmond, Virginia, July 9, 2014
    Biographical History: Wyatt Tee Walker, African American pastor, national civil rights leader, theologian, and cultural historian. He was educated at Virginia Union University, B.S. in chemistry and physics and the Virginia Union Graduate School of Theology. He was a chief of staff for Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr., and in 1958 became an early board member of the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC). He helped found a Congress for Racial Equality (CORE) chapter in 1958. As executive director of the SCLC from 1960 to 1964, Walker helped to bring the group to national prominence.
    Biographical History: Theresa Ann Walker was a civil rights worker and Freedom Rider.
    Summary: Dr. Walker reflects on his involvement in the freedom movement, especially his work as Martin Luther King's chief of staff and as the Executive Director of the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC) from 1960-1964. He recalls helping to organize the Children's Crusade in Birmingham, Alabama, and supporting Dr. King in transcribing and publishing Letter from a Birmingham Jail. He also remembers preaching in Petersburg, Virginia, and Harlem, New York, and becoming involved in several later movements, including anti-apartheid and pro-charter schools activism. Towards the end of the interview, his wife, Theresa Ann Walker, joins him on camera to talk briefly about her experiences in the movement.
    - Moving Images, 7 video files (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (01:13:19): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0109_mv01-07
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (.pdf): text file; afc2010039_crhp0109_ms01
  - Ellie Dahmer oral history interview conducted by Emilye Crosby in Hattiesburg, Mississippi, November 30, 2015
    Biographical History: Ellie Jewel Davis, born in Rose Hill, Mississippi, attended Alcorn State University and Tennessee A&I, and worked as a teacher throughout Mississippi. She married Vernon Ferdinand Dahmer, Sr. (1908-1966) in March of 1952. Vernon Dahmer was a leader in the Civil Rights Movement and president of the Forrest County chapter of the NAACP in Hattiesburg, Mississippi. On January 10, 1966, the Dahmer home was firebombed by the White Knights of the Ku Klux Klan. Though Ellie escaped with the children, Vernon died from resulting injuries.
    Summary: Ellie Dahmer discusses her involvement in the NAACP and voting rights activism in Forrest County, Mississippi. She recalls her experiences in education, both as a student at local schools, Alcorn State University, and Tennessee A&I, and as a teacher in schools throughout Mississippi. Her career as a Forrest County election commissioner is also discussed. She speaks about her husband, fellow activist Vernon Dahmer, and remembers the night when Klu Klux Klan members burned her home, killing her husband and injuring her children.
    - Moving Images, 7 video files (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (1:22:32): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0110_mv01-07
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (.pdf): text file; afc2010039_crhp0110_ms01
  - Peggy Jean Connor oral history interview conducted by Emilye Crosby in Hattiesburg, Mississippi, November 30, 2015
    Biographical History: Peggy Jean Connor is a strong movement activist, whose early involvement in voter registration included two important lawsuits. She was very active in Council of Federated Organizations (COFO) and Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party (MFDP).
    Summary: Peggy Jean Connor discusses her role in the Civil Rights Movement in southern Mississippi. She focuses particularly on voter registration, Freedom Day, being a Democratic National Convention delegate, the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), Council of Federated Organizations (COFO), her arrest, organizing the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party (MFDP), and the Connor v. Johnson lawsuit.
    - Moving Images, 7 video files (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (1:21:14): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0111_mv01-07
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (.pdf): text file; afc2010039_crhp0111_ms01
  - Raylawni G. Branch and Jeanette Smith oral history interview conducted by Emilye Crosby in Hattiesburg, Mississippi, December 1, 2015
    Biographical History: Jeanette Smith, Mississippi Civil Rights worker, worked with the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) and the Council of Federated Organizations (COFO).
    Biographical History: Raylawni G. Branch, Mississippi pioneer of the Civil Rights Movement, a professional nursing educator and US Air Force Reserve officer. She is best known for her leading role in the integration of the University of Southern Mississippi (Hattiesburg) in 1965.
    Summary: Raylawni G. Branch and Jeanette Smith discuss their involvement in the Hattiesburg, Mississippi-based Civil Rights Movement. They remember their upbringings as mixed race children, Smith in Mississippi and Branch in Mississippi and Chicago, Illinois. Branch recalls entering as one of the first black students at the University of Southern Mississippi. Both speak about their activism for voting rights and education, as well as sharing their philosophies on issues of race, discrimination, and activism.
    - Moving Images, 6 video files (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (2:36:43): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0112_mv01-06
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (.pdf): text file; afc2010039_crhp0112_ms01
  - Clarence Magee oral history interview conducted by Emilye Crosby in Hattiesburg, Mississippi, December 1, 2015
    Biographical History: Clarence Magee, born in 1932 in Columbia, Mississippi, was the oldest of ten children and was raised working on his parents' farm. He studied biology at Alcorn A&M graduating in 1954, and attended graduate school at Harvard. He served in the U.S. Army for two years and was stationed in Germany. After leaving the service he taught in several schools in Hattiesburg. He cofounded the Hattiesburg Association for Civic Improvement and was active in helping schools formulate desegregation plans. He was also involved in NAACP and in training for the Freedom Summer. He later worked for the Southern Mississippi Planning and Development Commission and the federal Department of Agriculture, Food, and Consumer Service office in Mobile, Alabama.
    Summary: Clarence Magee discusses the Civil Rights Movement in Mississippi. He recalls growing up in Marion County, Mississippi, where he was pushed by his family to pursue an education. He remembers becoming involved with the Hattiesburg branch of the NAACP after he was barred from registering to vote in 1956, then working in sensitivity training for Freedom Summer volunteers. He also discusses teaching in schools, working for the federal government, and co-founding the Hattiesburg Association for Civic Improvement.
    - Moving Images, 6 video files (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (1:50:33): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0113_mv01-06
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (.pdf): text file; afc2010039_crhp0113_ms01
  - Vernon Dahmer, Jr. oral history interview conducted by Emilye Crosby in Hattiesburg, Mississippi, December 1, 2015
    Biographical History: Vernon Dahmer, Jr. was born in 1929 in Kelly Settlement, Mississippi. The son of civil rights activist Vernon F. Dahmer, he joined the military in 1951, and after retiring from the Air Force, now resides in Hattiesburg, Mississippi.
    Summary: Vernon Dahmer, Jr., remembers growing up near Hattiesburg, Mississippi, and discusses his experiences relating to segregation and race, as a child and in the military. He also recalls the night his family's home in Hattiesburg was firebombed, killing his father, Vernon Dahmer, Sr., and his subsequent involvement in the trials of the Ku Klux Klan members who staged the bombing.
    - Moving Images, 12 video files (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (1:51:31): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0114_mv01-12
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (.pdf): text file; afc2010039_crhp0114_ms01
  - Eddie Holloway oral history interview conducted by Emilye Crosby in Hattiesburg, Mississippi, December 2, 2015
    Biographical History: Eddie Holloway was born in Hattiesburg, Mississippi in 1952. While he grew up in Hattiesburg, he also spent summers with family in Bessemer, Alabama. He enrolled at the University of Southern Mississippi in 1970. After graduating, he was employed at William Carey University and also worked in alcohol and drug treatment facilities. He eventually returned to work at USM for 40 years before he retired. In that time, he was the first African American to serve as Dean of Students, Assistant Vice President for Student Affairs.
    Summary: Eddie Holloway discusses growing up in Hattiesburg, Mississippi, as well as his involvement in Freedom Schools and other civil rights causes. He remembers his experiences as a child in a segregated society and school system, attending University of Southern Mississippi during its transition from a segregated to an integrated school, and his observations of the current educational environment as Dean of Students at USM.
    - Moving Images, 9 video files (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (2:13:09): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0115_mv01-09
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (.pdf): text file; afc2010039_crhp0115_ms01
  - Glenda Funchess oral history interview conducted by Emilye Crosby in Hattiesburg, Mississippi, December 2, 2015
    Biographical History: Glenda Funchess, born in 1954 in Hattiesburg, Mississippi, was one of the first African American children to attend the previously segregated, predominately white schools in Hattiesburg. She attended the participated in Freedom Summer and attended Freedom School at Mt. Zion Baptist Church. She currently practices law in Hattiesburg and teaches at the University of Southern Mississippi.
    Summary: Glenda Funchess speaks about her childhood in Hattiesburg, Mississippi. She remembers her experiences as one of the first children to desegregate Hattiesburg schools, as well as her involvement in Freedom Summer and at the Mount Zion Church Freedom School. She also discusses the relationship between churches and the Civil Rights Movement, and current civil rights activism and historical preservation.
    - Moving Images, 6 video files (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (1:23:57): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0116_mv01-06
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (.pdf): text file; afc2010039_crhp0116_ms01
  - Nathaniel Hawthorne Jones oral history interview conducted by Emilye Crosby in Claiborne County, Mississippi, December 3, 2015
    Biographical History: Nathaniel Hawthorne Jones was born in Claiborne County, Mississippi in 1914.
    Summary: Nathaniel Hawthorne Jones recalls his involvement in the Civil Rights Movement, specifically the Port Gibson Movement, in Mississippi. He discusses being drafted into the Navy in 1944 and the racial discrimination he experienced in his role as a Steward Mate. During the Port Gibson Movement, he was involved in the Port Gibson Merchant Boycotts, organizing protests at Alcorn College, and participating in voter registration activities.
    - Moving Images, 12 video files (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (1:53:28): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0117_mv01-12
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (.pdf): text file; afc2010039_crhp0117_ms01
  - Leesco Guster oral history interview conducted by Emilye Crosby in Port Gibson, Mississippi, December 3, 2015
    Biographical History: Leesco Guster was born in 1936 in Port Gibson, Mississippi. After growing up in various places in Mississippi, she briefly moved to Chicago before returning to Mississippi during the 1960s. She was heavily involved in voter registration is a lifetime member of the NAACP. She has operated a child day care center for over 30 years and continues to be active in her church community.
    Summary: Leesco Guster remembers experiencing segregation growing up and working in Port Gibson, Mississippi, and Chicago, Illinois. She recalls her work as an activist in Port Gibson, where she canvassed for voting rights, boycotted segregated businesses, and joined the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP). She also discusses churches' role in the Civil Rights Movement and her participation in the trial NAACP v. Claiborne Hardware Co.
    - Moving Images, 7 video files (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (1:15:13): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0118_mv01-07
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (.pdf): text file; afc2010039_crhp0118_ms01
  - Carolyn Miller and James Miller oral history interview conducted by Emilye Crosby in Port Gibson, Mississippi, December 4, 2015
    Biographical History: James E. Miller was born in 1949 and grew up in Port Gibson, Mississippi, where he met his wife, Carolyn Miller, in the youth group of the NAACP and participated in the Port Gibson boycotts. He was involved with Mississippi Cultural Crossroads and worked as County Administrator in Claiborne County, Mississippi.
    Biographical History: Carolyn Miller was born in Alcorn, Mississippi in 1953 and grew up in Hermanville and Port Gibson, Mississippi. She was involved in the youth chapter of the NAACP, where she met her husband, James Miller, and she participated in the Port Gibson boycotts. She taught at A. W. Watson elementary school, was involved in Mississippi Cultural Crossroads, and was a library board member.
    Summary: James and Carolyn Miller discuss their experience of living in Port Gibson, Mississippi during the Port Gibson Movement. They specifically reference the downtown merchant boycotts and how race and class tensions impacted the local community. They discuss their persistence in building interracial coalitions and emphasize the strength of local community building, political accountability and leadership for the sustainability of Port Gibson.
    - Moving Images, 9 video files (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (2:20:23): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0119_mv01-09
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (.pdf): text file; afc2010039_crhp0119_ms01
  - Patricia A. Crosby and David L. Crosby oral history interview, with Worth W. Long, Carolyn Miller and James Miller, conducted by Emilye Crosby in Port Gibson, Mississippi, December 4, 2015
    Biographical History: David L. Crosby is a civil rights activist. He co-founded Mississippi Cultural Crossroads in Port Gibson, Mississippi in 1976.
    Biographical History: Patricia A. Crosby is a civil rights activist. She co-founded Mississippi Cultural Crossroads in Port Gibson, Mississippi in 1976.
    Biographical History: Worth W. Long was born in 1936 in Durham, North Carolina. He joined the Air Force around 1953. In 1959, he was a student at Philander Smith College in Little Rock, Arkansas, he worked as a medic at the Little Rock Air Force base, served on the executive board of the Arkansas Council on Human Relations, and worked at Duke University Bale Research Lab in Durham, North Carolina. He became involved with organizing events in the civil rights movement as early as 1956, continuing through the 1960s, including participation in the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC). After the height of the civil rights movement, he was involved in folk music programming through the Smithsonian Folklife Festival, Delta Blues Festival, Louisiana Zydeco Festival in South Carolina, Penn Center Heritage Festival in Florida, and Zora Neale Hurston Festival. In 1977 he was funded by the Ford Foundation Leadership and Development program to study folklife and community empowerment with Alan Lomax at Columbia University. He joined the Mississippi Cultural Crossroads Board in 1980.